A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential records, Foreign Affairs and National Security, Series 19 FA385
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller vice presidential records, Foreign Affairs and National Security, Series 19
1974-1977
Rockefeller Archive Center
United States. Office of the Vice President
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
FA385
18.6 Cubic Feet
17 record cartons 4 document boxes
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical/Historical note
President Gerald R. Ford nominated Nelson A. Rockefeller to fill the vacant vice presidency following the resignation of President Richard M. Nixon in August 1974. Rockefeller served as Vice President from December 19, 1974, to January 20, 1977.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 26 19
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson A. Rockefeller served as the second unelected Vice President in the history of the United States. (President Gerald Ford, whom Rockefeller served as Vice President, had been the first unelected Vice President.) Although Mr. Rockefeller acted relatively extensively in the areas of foreign relations and national security, his main focus, in the view of many observers, was on domestic policy. At the same time, the work that commanded the greatest public attention during the Ford-Rockefeller Administration was that of the CIA Commission. The recommendations issued by the commission strongly affected the policy and operation of the CIA for a generation.
Jonathan T. Howe graduated from the U.S. Naval Academy in 1957 and earned a Ph.D. from the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, Tufts University in 1969. His early career in the Navy was spent on submarines. Prior to serving with Vice President Rockefeller, he was on the National Security Council staff as military assistant to the Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs, 1969 to 1974. Later appointments included senior military assistant to the Deputy Secretary of Defense, 1981 to 1982; Assistant to the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, 1987 to 1989; and Deputy Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs, 1991 to 1993. He also served in Somalia as the Special Representative of the UN Secretary-General, 1993 to 1994, and after retirement from the Navy, he ran a philanthropic foundation.
Arrangement note
The arrangement of the series, while mainly by broad topic, is inconsistent on occasion. However, the folder order has been kept intact to maintain a direct correlation to the separated, classified pages. For this same reason, there are no Folders 122 to 192.
Other Findings Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Richard Allison (FA377)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Central Files (FA378)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, National Commission on Water Quality (FA379)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, New York Office (FA380)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Joseph E. Persico (FA381)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Press Releases (FA382)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Speeches (FA383)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Working Papers of the Vice President (FA384)
Scope and Contents note
The bulk of this series of papers consists of files kept by Captain Jonathan T. Howe, Assistant to the Vice President for National Security Affairs, who served Nelson A. Rockefeller during his entire vice presidency (December 19, 1974 to January 20, 1977) in the Gerald R. Ford Administration. The contents reflect international relations and national security topics that Capt. Howe monitored closely for the Vice President. He also oversaw Mr. Rockefeller's appointment schedule on these matters and coordinated with Peter Wallison, Counsel to the Vice President, on suggested responses to inquiries involving foreign officials or national security issues.
The topics covered include International Travel, National Security, Meetings with Foreign Dignitaries, Meetings with U.S. Officials, the Commission on the Organization of the Government for the Conduct of Foreign Policy (Murphy Commission), Intelligence, Countries/Regions, and the Commission on CIA Activities Within the United States (alternately Rockefeller or CIA Commission). Additionally, there are several folders of background information on the Operations Coordinating Board, which originate from Mr. Rockefeller's tenure as Special Assistant to President Eisenhower during the mid-1950s. Also significant in this series are monthly folders of Captain Howe's chron file. (See topic descriptions below.)
Noticeably absent is documentation of direct communication between the Vice President and President Ford on any of these matters. However, there are numerous memos throughout the series from Secretary of State Henry Kissinger--particularly under International Travel--and National Security Affairs Assistant Brent Scowcroft--particularly under National Security Council Meetings.
The arrangement of the series, while mainly by broad topic, is inconsistent on occasion. However, the folder order has been kept intact to maintain a direct correlation to the separated, classified pages. For this same reason, there are no Folders 122 to 192.
Additionally, some folder numbers use a decimal extension (for example, Folder 13.1, Folder 336.4). This designation can mean that either it is a folder created to subdivide an overfilled original folder or it is a closed folder of restricted documents. The latter are prominently labeled as such in the folder list.
DESCRIPTION
International Travel (Folders 1-57) ranges from the Vice President serving as the official U.S. representative at funerals of foreign dignitaries or national celebrations to meetings with heads of state or their top ministers. In 1976 he attended several international celebrations to commemorate the U.S. Bicentennial. Some personal travel files exist as well. Every trip includes a substantial amount of U.S. State Department cables, itineraries, background information on the countries being visited, cultural protocol tips, and follow-up correspondence.
National Security folders are scattered throughout the series but include titles such as National Security Council Meetings, Defense Department Briefings, Cruise Missiles, and Pertinent National Security Developments. Intelligence-related folders also crop up sporadically; Intelligence Review and Reorganization, President's Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board (PFIAB), and Terrorism are a few title examples.
Meetings with Foreign Dignitaries (Folders 64-88) include arrangements, agenda, and either notes or verbatim accounts of the discussions. They are arranged by mouth in roughly reverse chronological order. Meetings with U.S. Officials (Folders 93-97) have similar contents but are less numerous. They too are arranged in roughly reverse chronological order. See the Materials of Special Significance section for specific names and dates of significant meetings with those officials.
In January 1975, President Ford recommended that Vice President Rockefeller fill an open seat on the Commission on the Organization of the Government for the Conduct of Foreign Policy, more commonly referred to as the Murphy Commission. The commission was established by an act of Congress in June 1972, and it concluded its work in June 1975. Capt. Howe often sat in for the Vice President at the commission meetings. Folders 103-121 hold correspondence, agenda, report drafts, press clippings, and meeting minutes. Folder 120 contains a thorough summary of the history of the commission, including a candid memo on its workings and aftermath written by Capt. Howe to Mr. Rockefeller in January 1977.
Additionally, the contents of more than 30 binders of working papers and background information on the Murphy Commission are at the end of this series in Folders 393-429. Items labeled Books directly correlate to commission meetings during the Vice President's tenure. A tab-level listing of their contents is provided. Items labeled Background Workbooks are background materials from meetings in 1973 and 1974, prior to Mr. Rockefeller's membership on the commission. There is no tab-level listing for them, but the folders are grouped by topic (e.g., intelligence, internationals economics). Lastly, the eight-volume set of the published final report of the Murphy Commission (1 report volume and 7 appendices) has been removed from this series and added to the RAC library collection (library catalog #353.001 COM).
Folders 232-284 cover issues on specific countries/regions, from Angola to Yugoslavia. These files may contain duplicates of documents found under International Travel but often have unique ones. They are arranged in semi-alphabetical order by country name.
Captain Jon Howe's Chron Files (Folders 314-320.5 and 333-344) are an informative source on both the daily activities of the Office of the Vice President and the significant national and international events during those years. They are arranged by month in approximate reverse chronological order. A few reference files are interspersed among them.
In December 1974 at President Ford's request, Nelson Rockefeller became chair of the newly appointed Commission on CIA Activities Within the United States, which was established by Executive Order as a result of ongoing claims of abuse of jurisdiction against the federal agency. The commission, which came to be known as both the Rockefeller Commission and the CIA Commission, is documented from its inception to its final report in Folders 322-332.2 and 346-392. Also among these files are Cold War-era materials from the Operations Coordinating Board that contain information on studies on psychological warfare, Soviet military capabilities, and the Quantico Panel from 1953 to 1955. They are all contemporaneous with Mr. Rockefeller's service in President Eisenhower's Administration as Special Assistant to the President for Foreign Affairs.
MATERIALS OF SPECIAL SIGNIFICANCE
Numerous folders in this series contain materials of special significance for research on Nelson Rockefeller as Vice President, on national intelligence, and on international affairs during the mid-1970s.
One distinction from other series in the Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers is that these records contain copious amounts of handwritten notes by the Vice President. In particular, refer to Folder 121, NAR Notes on Murphy Commission, 1975; Folder 327, CIA Commission, NAR's Handwritten Notes, 1975; Folder 350, Memo to President from Donald Rumsfeld on CIA Directorship, June 1975; Folders 352 to 353.1, NAR Drafts to CIA Commission Report Chapters, May 1975; and Folders 393 to 420, Murphy Commission Books I-XXVIII.
There is substantial content on meetings between Vice President Rockefeller and foreign or U.S. officials, including some verbatim accounts. Documentation on meetings with foreign dignitaries, U.S. Defense Department officials, and other U.S. officials are organized by month in Folders 64 to 97. Memoranda of conversations are grouped by year in Folders 98 to 100.1. While this arrangement does not enumerate the names of these people, the following alphabetical list provides dates of meetings between the Vice President and these heads of state and other significant officials:
George H. W. Bush, CIA Director, March 1976. President Valerie Giscard D'Estaing of France, March 1976. General Alexander Haig, NATO Commander, November 1975 and May 1976. Emperor Hirohito of Japan, October 1975. King Hussein of Jordan, April 1975. King Juan Carlos of Spain, November 1975. King Khalid and Crown Prince Fahd of Saudi Arabia, March 1975. Henry Kissinger, Secretary of State (see folders on International Travel and Countries and Folders 213-215.1). Reza Shah Pahlavi of Iran, May 1975 and March 1976 (see also Folder 241). Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin of Israel, September 1974 and January 1976. President Anwar Sadat of Egypt, March and October 1975. Brent Scowcroft, Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs (see folders on NSC Meetings, 1975-1977). Senator Tran Van Lam of the Republic of Viet Nam, February 1975. U.S. Joint Chiefs of Staff, April 1976. Paul A. Volcker, economic consultant, May 1975. Kurt Waldheim, UN Secretary-General, June 1975. Prime Minister Harold Wilson of the United Kingdom, January, July, September 1975.
Related Archival Materials note
Researchers may also wish to consult other portions of the Nelson A. Rockefeller (NAR) Papers, in particular Group 4: NAR Personal, Series O: Washington, DC, Subseries 7: Special Assistant to the President for Foreign Affairs for additional materials on the Operations Coordinating Board from the 1950s. Also, in Record Group 26: NAR Vice Presidential, refer to Series 3: Central Files, Series 13: Press Releases, Series 15: Speeches, and Series 18: Working Papers of the Vice President.
Custodial History
This series contains documents that were declassified by the U.S. government during a review by government officials at the Archive Center from 2003 to 2006. Any document that remains classified since the review has been removed from its folder and replaced with a separation sheet to note its original and current locations. Therefore, all materials in the open folders is now declassified, whether or not the classification stamps on them indicate otherwise. Almost all of the declassified documents prominently display a federal agency's declassification stamp and date.
Water -- Purification; Water -- Pollution; Water conservation; Vice-Presidents -- United States; Human rights; International economic relations; Federal government -- United States; Government policy; United States; Veterans -- United States; International relations; Technology; Economics; Education; Drug control; Economic policy; Environmental policy; Environmental sciences; Education -- United States; Energy; Prevention and health; Public health; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1976; Political science; Presidential campaigns -- United States; International relations -- United States; National security -- United States; Social problems; Social sciences; Public policy; Social policy
- Saudi Arabia Substance File, March 25-28, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Saudi Arabia Trip, March 25-28, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Saudi Arabia Trip, March 25-28, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2.1)
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Restricted material
- Republic of China, April 13-17, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- European Trip Thank-You Letters, July 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- European Trip Thank-You Letters, July 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4.1)
- Vice President's European Trip, June 26-July 8, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Vice President's European Trip, June 26-July 8, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5.1)
- Franklin-Jefferson Exhibition in London Thank-You Letters (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Franklin-Jefferson Exhibition in London Substance File (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Franklin-Jefferson Exhibition in London, September 14-16, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Spain Substance File, November 21-27, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Spain Substance File, November 21-27, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9.1)
- Around the World Trip, March 20-April 4, 1976; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Around the World Trip, March 20-April 4, 1976; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 10.1)
- Around the World Trip (from Folder 10), March 20-April 4, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10.2)
- Around the World Substance File, March 20-April 4, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Around the World Trip (from Folder 10.1), March 20-April 4, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10.3)
- Overflight Messages from World Trip, March 20-April 4, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Around the World Substance File, March 20-April 4, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12.1)
- West Germany Trip, May 13-15, 1976; Folder 1 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- West Germany Trip, May 13-15, 1976; Folder 2 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 13.1)
- West Germany Trip, May 13-15, 1976; Folder 3 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 13.2)
- West Germany Trip (from Folder 13), May 13-15, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13.3)
- West Germany Trip (from Folder 13.2), May 13-15, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13.4)
- Press Comments on Germany-Italy Trip, May 13-15, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Germany-Italy Trip Substance File, May 13-15, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Germany-Italy Trip Substance File, May 13-15, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 15.1)
- Italy & Germany, May 13-15, 1976; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Italy & Germany, May 13-15, 1976; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 16.1)
- Italy and Germany (from Folder 16.1), May 13-15, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 16.2)
- Italy & Germany Background, May 13-15, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- State Cables - London Trip, October 3-5, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- State Cables - London Trip, October 3-5, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 18.1)
- London Trip for Indian Art Exhibition, October 3-5, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- London Trip for Indian Art Exhibition, October 3-5, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 19.1)
- Vacation to Venezuela - Message List, December 26-31, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Venezuela Trip, December 26-31, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Venezuela Trip, December 26-31, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 21.1)
- President's Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board (PFIAB) Documents - Pre-Vice Presidential, July 1974 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Department of State Briefing Book on Tunisia, March 1976 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- NAR Visits, March 19-April 4, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Visit to Tunisia, March 20-21, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Visit to Tunisia, March 20-21, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 25.1)
- Visit to Paris, March 21-23, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Visit to Paris, March 21-23, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 26.1)
- Department of State Briefing Book on France, March 1976 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Department of State Briefing Book on Iran, March 1976 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Trip to Kish Island, Iran, March 23-26, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Trip to Kish Island, Iran, March 23-26, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 29.1)
- Trip to Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, March 26-28, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Trip to Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, March 26-28, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 30.1)
- Department of State Briefing Book on Malaysia, March 1976 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Department of State Briefing Book on Malaysia, March 1976 (Box 2, Folder 31.1)
- Department of State Briefing Book on Singapore, March 1976 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Visit to Singapore, March 28-29, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Visit to Singapore, March 28-29, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 33.1)
- Visit to Bali; Visit to Tahiti, March 29 and April 2-4, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  Scope and Contents note
  Visit to Bali, March 29, 1976; Visit to Tahiti, April 2-4, 1976.
- Visit to Bali, Indonesia, March 29, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Memorandum to the President from Brent Scowcroft (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Department of State Briefing Book on Germany and United Kingdom, May-June 1975 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Trip to United Kingdom Message File, September 1975 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Trip to Europe, July 1975 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Trip to Europe, July 1975 (Box 3, Folder 39.1)
- Trip to Europe Message File, June 26-July 8, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Trip to Europe Message File, June 26-July 8, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 40.1)
- Australia Trip, March 1976 (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Australia Trip, March 1976 (Box 3, Folder 41.1)
- New Zealand Trip, April 1-3, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- New Zealand Trip, APril 1-3, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 42.1)
- Department of State Briefing Brook on New Zealand, April 1976 (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Tahiti, French Polynesia, and Thailand Trip, March 25-27, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Tahiti, French Polynesia, and Thailand Trip, March 25-27, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 44.1)
- Public Statements in France and Tunisia, March 1976 (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Briefing Book for Mrs. Rockefeller, Seven-Nation Trip, March-April 1976 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Briefing Book for Mrs. Rockefeller, Seven-Nation Trip, March-April 1976 (Box 3, Folder 46.1)
- VP Briefing Book on Visit to Berlin and Frankfurt, Germany, May 13-15, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Department of State Briefing Book on Australia, March 1976 (Box 3, Folder 48)
- National Security Issues - Asian Strategy Briefing Book, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Trip to Germany, May 13-15, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Taipei Trip Message File, April 1975 (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Trip to Italy, May 13, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 52)
- Presidential Delegation to Saudi Arabia, March 1975 (Box 3, Folder 53)
- Vice President's Mission to Spain, November 1975 (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Spain Trip Message File, November 1975 (Box 3, Folder 55)
- VP Briefing Book on Visit to London, October 1-3, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 56)
- Department of State Briefing Book on Taiwan, April 1975 (Box 3, Folder 57)
- National Security Council Meetings - General, January-June 1976 (Box 4, Folder 58)
- National Security Council Meetings - General, July-December 1976 (Box 4, Folder 59)
- National Security Council Semiannual Review, January 13, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 60)
- National Security Council Meetings, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 61)
- Commission on CIA Activities Within the United States, May 1975-July 1975 (Box 4, Folder 62)
- Strategic Arms Limitation Talks (SALT), January 1975-August 1976 (Box 4, Folder 63)
- Meetings with Foreign Dignitaries, 1975-1977
  - February 1976 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - March 1976 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - March 1976 (Box 4, Folder 65.1)
  - April 1976 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - September 1976 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - September 1976 (Box 4, Folder 67.1)
  - October 1976 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - November 1976 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - January 1977 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - December 1976 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - May 1976, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - May 1976, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 72.1)
  - June 1976, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - June 1976, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 73.1)
  - July 1976 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - August 1976 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - November 1975 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - December 1975 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - January 1976 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - October 1975 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - August 1975 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - August 1975 (Box 5, Folder 80.1)
  - September 1975 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - July 1975 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - June 1975 (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - May 1975, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - May 1975, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 84.1)
  - April 1975 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - March 1975 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - February 1975 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - January 1975 (Box 5, Folder 88)
- Address to Inter-American Defense College, June 10, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 89)
- Meetings with Defense Department, 1975-1976; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 90)
- Meetings with Defense Department, 1975-1976; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 90.1)
- Meetings with Defense Department (from Folder 90), 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 90.2)
- Visit to Newport News, Virginia, October 11, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 91)
- Defense Department Briefings, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 92)
- Defense Department Briefings, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 92.1)
- Meetings with U.S. Officials, January-June 1976 (Box 5, Folder 93)
- Meetings with U.S. Officials, July-December 1976 (Box 5, Folder 94)
- Meetings with U.S. Officials, January 1977 (Box 5, Folder 95)
- Meetings with U.S. Officials, July-December 1975 (Box 5, Folder 96)
- Meetings with U.S. Officials, January-June 1975 (Box 5, Folder 97)
- Memoranda of Conversation, 1976; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 98)
- Memoranda of Conversation, 1976; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 98.1)